, גוט ערב פסח. Gut Erev Pesach. Everybody who's here today is
through מסירות נפש. mesiras nefesh. Make sure you do your ביטול bittul
and your burning. Okay, so today's דף daf is י"ח. Yud Ches.
We pick up at the bottom of י"ז עמוד ב' Yud Zayin
Amud Beis and we are really going to be focusing for a
lot of this פרק perek and certainly for today on this question
about what is the type of ספק safeik needed to bring an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. Again, an אשם תלוי asham talui is that
you ate something thinking it was היתר, heter, it turns out that
you might have done a sin. If you knew for sure you
did a sin, you'd bring a חטאת chattas if it was a
חייב כרת, chayav kares, but you now only know you might have,
so you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui until you can clarify
what it was. As רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both say, if
at the time you knew that it was a ספק safeik and
you went ahead and did it anyway, then you don't bring an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. רש"י Rashi says מזיד, mezid, which is a
little harsh way of describing it because you didn't willfully sin, you
knew it was a ספק. safeik. תוספות Tosafot rather quotes the phrase
called שב מידיעתה, shov ni'di'ata, which means that normally שוגג shogeg is
had you known the facts you wouldn't have done it. Here you
knew the facts and you did it anyway. You knew the facts
that it was a ספק, safeik, so we cannot bring a קרבן.
korban. Okay, so the point is at the time you thought it
was מותר mutar and then afterwards you found out you might have
sinned. Now the big question is what constitutes the possibility of sin?
So the way this is framed in the גמרא Gemara is because
the classic case in the משנה Mishnah was you ate something and
it might have been שומן shuman and it might have been חלב.
chelev. So is it enough that there was one piece in front
of you and there's some reason to think it was problematic, or
do you need there to be two pieces and one was definitely
חלב chelev and the question is which one did you eat? Is
it חתיכה אחת chaticha achas or שתי חתיכות? shtei chatichos? Until now
we've been saying it's a debate based on the פסוקים, pesukim, whether
the פסוק pasuk is read מצוות mitzvos or written מצות, mitzvas, and
we haven't given any סברא svara for it, logic for it, just
focused on the פסוקים. pesukim. We are now going to move into
continuing that debate but actually seeing different logic, different reasons given for
why it makes a difference to have two pieces rather than one.
The reason should be relatively obvious, but the גמרא Gemara is now
going to start spelling it out. So we pick up on the
bottom of י"ז עמוד ב' Yud Zayin Amud Beis and we are
five lines into the wide lines,
or actually the last word on the fourth line. אמר רבי חייא
בר אבא היו לפניו שתי חתיכות, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, hayu
lefanav shtei chatichos, if you had two pieces of food in front
of you, אחת של חלב ואחת של שומן, achas shel chelev ve'achas
shel shuman, one was definitely forbidden fat, one was permissible, ואכל אחת
מהן ואין יודע איזה מהן אכל, ve'achal achas mehen ve'ein yodeia eizeh
mehen achal, you ate one and you didn't know which one, again
assuming at the time you thought it was all היתר, heter, חייב,
chayav, then you bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. חתיכה ספק של
שומן ספק של חלב, Chaticha safeik shel shuman safeik shel chelev, if
it was only one piece of food and you didn't know what
its status was, or even and it was not known what its
status was, ואכלה, ve'achalah, you ate it and then you found out
it might have been חלב, chelev, פטור, patur, you're exempt. So again,
you need שתי חתיכות shtei chatichos where one was definitely forbidden, not
one which was doubtful forbidden. אמר רבי זירא מאי טעמא דרב, Amar
Rabbi Zeira, mai ta'ama deRav, what's the reason? Until now we've been
quoting פסוקים, pesukim, now we start looking at reasons. קסבר, Kasavar, because
רב Rav is of the opinion, שתי חתיכות אפשר לברר איסורו חתיכה
אחת אי אפשר לברר איסורו. shtei chatichos efshar levarer issuro, chaticha achas
ee efshar levarer issuro.
Maybe not what we would have initially have thought, but this question
was raised yesterday, which is is it ever possible you'll get to
the bottom of the facts? So if there were two pieces and
somebody you thought they were both היתר heter but somebody came and
informed you one was היתר heter and one was איסור, issur, you
actually can figure out, find out what you did. You look at
the other one and you figure out what it is. Okay, the
גמרא Gemara is going to get to that. But at least at
the time of the sin, there was the potential of figuring out
whether or not you had actually done the sin or not, right?
Because we could have inspected the other one. And therefore an אשם
תלוי asham talui is often seen not just to atone for the
here and now, but basically to tide you over to protect you
until it can be determined whether you really have to bring a
חטאת chattas or not. So if you could determine it, then we
have the ability of clarifying and then you'll have the אשם תלוי
asham talui until it can be determined, but we
know
in
theory it can be
determined, which is a case of two pieces and you could inspect
the second one.
Yes, so let me understand. So as you said the גמרא Gemara
is going to get to it. If there's no way of ever
determining, even in the case of two pieces, like both animals were
eaten and the whole animal whatever it is, then there's no way.
Right, so are they going to bring an אשם תלוי asham talui
because conceptually you need to bring it? Because at the time of
the sin you could have. But if at the time of the
sin that you couldn't have, then the answer will be no. The
גמרא Gemara will get to it, so hold off, you'll see it
in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so that's the reason given whether it's
אפשר לברר efshar levarer or not
אפשר לברר. efshar levarer. איתיביה רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא, Eisivei Rabbi Yirmiya
leRabbi Zeira, so רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya asked רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
who quoted this position of רב. Rav. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
omer, so now it's going to be a complete... repeat of what
we saw yesterday a whole series of positions which show that we
do an אשם תלוי asham talui even if it's only one חתיכה.
chatichah. Okay and the consistent answer's going to be yes there's an
opposing position out there רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's not my position.
Okay so now we're going to have a whole series of cases
where you bring it only with one חתיכה. chatichah. So let's take
a look. רבי אליעזר אומר כוי חייב עליו על חלבו אשם תלוי.
Rabbi Eliezer omer koy chayav alav al chelvo asham talui.
If you eat a חלב chelev of a כוי koy which is
questionable בהמה behemah questionable חיה chayah as a בהמה behemah its fat
would be forbidden if it's a חיה chayah its fat would be
permissible so you bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So that's not
two חתיכות. chatichos. We're never going to determine the status. The whole
idea of this כוי koy is that it has an indeterminate status.
So you see you bring it even without אפשר לברר. efshar levarer.
אמר ליה רבי אליעזר סבר לא בעינן לברר איסורא פאי. Amar lei
Rabbi Eliezer savar lo bayinan levarer issura pai. Fine רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer is the opposing position. He holds that one חתיכה chatichah you
don't need to determine. I hold that you need two חתיכות. chatichos.
איתיביה Eisivei so I'll ask you again. ספק בן תשעה לראשון או
בן שבעה לאחרון Safek ben tishah larishon o ben shivah la-acharon again
this woman whose husband died she had יבום yibum with the brother
and then she got pregnant
after seven months. You don't know if it's from the first husband
and therefore
the marriage to this brother is עריות arayos is forbidden. So what
do you do? יוציא Yotzi so he has to get divorced because
it might be a case of עריות. arayos. והולד כשר Ve-havlad kasher
the child is כשר kasher as Michael explained correctly yesterday because regardless
if it was a child of the first one then he's not
a ממזר. mamzer. If it's a child of the second one then
there was a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum and he's also not
a ממזר. mamzer. So the child is regardless כשר kasher but they
might have been engaging in עריות arayos if it was a child
of the first one if there was no מצות יבום. mitzvas yibum.
וחייבין באשם תלוי Ve-chayavin be-asham talui and you bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. So here again this is a woman that at least
before genetic testing you're never going to determine whether there was a
מצות יבום mitzvas yibum or not whether the child was the first
husband's or the second. And we say you bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui.
They both
would the woman they both would bring an אשם תלוי asham talui
even though there's no two חתיכות chatichos there's no אפשר לברר. efshar
levarer. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר הא מני רבי אליעזר היא.
Amar ha mani Rabbi Eliezer hi. Fine it's the same רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer we quoted before who says even without two חתיכות chatichos
even without אפשר לברר. efshar levarer. איתיביה Eisivei another again these are
all the questions we asked yesterday that prove even one חתיכה. chatichah.
נמצא על שלה אלתר טמאה וחייבת בקרבן. Nimtza al shelah altar temeah
ve-chayaves be-korban. A man and woman have sex husband and wife and
then it turns out that she's bleeding. And the question is was
she a נדה niddah when they had sex or not or did
she only become a נדה niddah afterwards? So if she finds it
on her you know cloth that she wiped with if she found
it immediately after they separated then we assume that she was bleeding
at the time of sex and therefore she was a נדה niddah
and they didn't do it intentionally so they bring a קרבן. korban.
נמצא על שלה לאחר זמן טמאה מספק Nimtza al shelah le-achar zman
temeah misafek if it was on her the thing she wiped with
but it was after a while then טמאה מספק temeah misafek then
you don't know had she been a נדה niddah at the time
of sex or only after? So then they're טמא tamei only doubtfully
טמא. tamei. Actually now she's definitely טמאה. temeah. He is not definitely
טמא tamei because his טומאה tumah would be based on whether he
was having sex with her when she was a נדה niddah or
not. Anyway טומאה tumah is not our focus. ופטורין מן הקרבן U-pturin
min ha-korban they don't bring a חטאת chatas because we don't know
for sure that she was a נדה niddah when they had sex.
ותניא עלה וחייבין באשם תלוי Ve-tanya alah ve-chayavin be-asham talui but we
have a ברייתא braisa that clarifies
that they at least have to bring an אשם תלוי asham talui
because it's possible they had sex when she was a נדה. niddah.
So again there's no other facts that can come to light there's
no way of ever determining it or not. So this is a
case of one חתיכה chatichah as it was אי אפשר לברר ee
efshar levarer and you're still bringing an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So
once again the answer is הא מני רבי אליעזר היא. Ha mani
Rabbi Eliezer hi. Fine it's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So we have
these three cases of אשם תלוי asham talui which are clearly one
חתיכה chatichah and the גמרא Gemara says fine there is a position
out there of one חתיכה chatichah but that is not necessarily the
position of our משנה. Mishnah. We are arguing that you need two
חתיכות chatichos and now the reason is אפשר לברר. efshar levarer. So
one we have a reason of a פסוק pasuk one we have
a reason of אפשר לברר. efshar levarer. Okay now let's go on.
Now we're going to have a third reason. Wait did I skip
a line? Hold on a minute. You know what I did? I
skipped a line before. I'm very sorry I skipped an important line.
Okay so if you go back and look I think from
yeah no wait a minute.
Did I skip a line? Yes I skipped a line. Go back
I'm sorry four lines from the bottom of י"ז עמוד ב' Yud
Zayin Amud Beis because this is an important point. Four lines from
the bottom of the middle of the line I skipped this.
מאי איכא בין טעמא דרבא לטעמא דרבי זירא? Mai ika bein taama
de-Rava le-taama de-Rabbi Zeira? Do you see that? Now if you okay
I somehow skipped over that. What is the difference between whether the
reason is just a פסוק pasuk that demands two חתיכות chatichos or
whether it's a logic of אפשר לברר? efshar levarer? Okay here's the
גמרא Gemara clarifying the difference of how we explain the need for
two חתיכות. chatichos. So it says איכא בינייהו כזית ומחצה. Ika beiniyahu
kezayis u-mechsah. The question is let's say you have two pieces of
food in front of you one is a כזית kezayis one is
a half a כזית. kezayis. One is חלב chelev one is שומן
shuman you don't know which is which. Okay now in that case
and you ate one is it אפשר לברר? efshar levarer? Sure because
you could test the one that remains the half a כזית kezayis
that remains you can test it and determine what you did. But
were there two מצוות mitzvos two full
two full candidates for an act of eating? No, only one was
a כזית, kezayit, only one would have been defined as a full
object. Okay, לרבא ליכא מצוות, leRava leika mitzvot, according to Rava there's
not מצוות, mitzvot, he goes for a פסוק, pasuk, a just a
formal requirement of two, חצי כזית chatzi kezayit is not full, so
you would not satisfy it, ופטור upatur you'd be exempt. לרבי זירא
אפשר לברר איסורא, leRabbi Zeira efshar levarer issura, and according to Rabbi
Zeira though, you could just still test the remaining חצי כזית. chatzi
kezayit. Okay, so that's the גמרא Gemara if it's a need of
a פסוק, pasuk, you need two full things, if it's a need
of being able to test, then you wouldn't need two full as
long as you can test. For example, I gave an example right
now, nowadays in the case where you have one חתיכה chaticha and
you could test, like the case about this woman and which husband
was she pregnant from? Nowadays you could do a blood test or
genetic testing, so if it's about testing, it leads to different conclusions
than being about a formal requirement of two. Okay, those are the
two opinions right now, and now we get a third opinion. Back
to י"ח ע"א. yud chet amud aleph. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אמר
רב נחמן amar Rav Nachman about six lines down, אמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב. amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar
Avuha amar Rav. So now again another statement in the name of
רב, Rav, the same statement, היו לפניו שתי חתיכות hayu lefanav shtei
chatichot if you have two pieces, אחת של חלב ואחת של שומן,
achat shel chelev ve'achat shel shuman, one fat and one שומן, shuman,
ואכל אחת מהן ואין ידוע איזה מהן אכל, ve'achal achat mehen ve'ein
yaduah eizeh mehen achal, you ate one you don't know, חייב, chayav,
then you're חייב chayav because there were two pieces. חתיכה ספק של
חלב ספק של שומן chaticha safek shel chelev safek shel shuman if
it was one piece and you don't know, or anyway at the
time you thought it was all okay, then you then you found
out it might have been
improper, ואכלה פטור, ve'achalah patur, you're exempt. So again שתי חתיכות חייב,
shtei chatichot chayav, אחת חתיכה פטור. achat chaticha patur. So so far
it's what we've been saying, but the key is how it's explained.
אמר רב נחמן מאי טעמא דרב, amar Rav Nachman mai ta'ama deRav,
what's the reasoning of רב? Rav? Not like we said before because
of אפשר לברר, efshar levarer, here's a new explanation for רב Rav
and this is the one which is most commonly quoted and I
think is most intuitive, קסבר שתי חתיכות אקבע איסורא, kasavar shtei chatichot
ikva issura, חתיכה אחת לא קבע איסורא. chaticha achat lo kava issura.
Two חתיכות chatichot the איסור issur has been established. One חתיכה chaticha
it has not been established, which is very clear. If you found
out that there is definitely חלב chelev in front of you, then
you know looking back at that act that you did an act
where there was a concrete
possibility that had you done a particular thing you would have sinned.
You just don't know did you eat piece A or piece B?
But had you eaten piece A, there was unquestionably you would have
sinned. So there is an established איסור issur in front of you.
If however you don't know whether this piece ever was איסור issur
or היתר, heter, it could be that you know it's just your
in doubt, but the reality was at the time it was only
היתר heter in front of you. There wasn't the objective reality of
a sin in front of you and the question is did you
go down the path of sin or the path of היתר? heter?
You maybe the whole thing was a path of היתר, heter, you
just were in doubt. So what he says is in order to
bring an אשם תלוי asham talui you don't just need the possibility
that you sinned. It could be a very good possibility, fifty-fifty by
the כוי koy or with whose child this was, it could be
a very serious possibility, but that's not enough. You need the fact
that there was definitely a concrete sin in front of you. And
the question was just did you choose it or not? אקבע איסורא
ikva issura you need it to have been established, the איסור issur
established, and only then does it lead to an אשם תלוי. asham
talui. Now I want to say that conceptually, right, this might point
you to think of an אשם תלוי asham talui a little differently.
If an אשם תלוי asham talui is to protect me from punishment
or whatever it is until I bring a חטאת, chatat, the possibility
of sin maybe is enough. But if the אשם תלוי asham talui
is like a
quasi-חטאת, chatat, right, it's like not just maybe I sinned, there was
actually something intrinsically problematic in the act itself even if I didn't
sin. You could see that more when there's the real concrete thing
in front of me that's איסור. issur. Having eaten something when it
was concretely in front of me is already an inherently problematic thing
even if it turns out that what I did later was what
I ate the right thing. It doesn't matter. Having eaten something when
there was a concrete איסור issur in front of me even if
you were oblivious to it is an inherently problematic act. Okay, so
that's maybe also a way about thinking about it. It's not just
the it's not just that it's that maybe you sinned, there's something
more inherently problematic when there was something אסור assur right in front
of you.
Yeah. You're saying until you can bring a חטאת. chatat. Right. What
is what does that mean in practicality?
Meaning until you
find out that if you find out that you definitely did sin
or definitely didn't sin, then you that would be the end of
it. But if but
you might go your whole life not finding out or you might
at least, you know, go six months and you want a קרבן
korban to atone for
you or protect you until you're able to. That's what
it is.
So if you find out in six months you did
sin, you would bring the חטאת. chatat. Yes, absolutely. And we'll discuss
that later what happens when later you
get clarified. Okay, so now anyway that's the idea of אקבע איסורא.
ikva issura.
So now let's see where the גמרא Gemara continues. Right, and you
find out in six months you sinned and you would bring the
חטאת. chatas.
Yes, absolutely, and we'll discuss that later, what happens when later you
get clarified. Okay, so now anyway that's the idea of איקבע איסורא.
ikva issura. So now let's see where the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay,
מאי ביני mai bini איקבע איסורא ikva issura לשאי אפשר לברר. le-she-ee
efshar levareir.
What would be a scenario where it would be a difference between
the reason of איקבע איסורא ikva issura or אי אפשר לברר? ee
efshar levareir? So the איסורא. issura. So the גמרא Gemara says, and
this is similar to questions Michael's asking before, איכא בינייהו כגון שהיו
לפניו שתי חתיכות. ika beinaihu kegon she-hayu lefanav shtei chatichot.
You had the two pieces, you started with them, אחת של חלב
ואחת של שומן, achat shel chelev ve-achat shel shuman, one was definitely
חלב, chelev, one שומן. shuman. You of course were oblivious, but we
happen to know that was the facts. ובא עובד כוכבים ואכל את
הראשונה. u-va oved kochavim ve-achal et ha-rishona. A non-Jew came, meaning the
reason we're saying non-Jew is because we don't have to then discuss
whether he was חייב. chayav. A non-Jew came and he ate one
piece. ובא ישראל ואכל את השנייה, u-va Yisrael ve-achal et ha-shniya, and
then you came and you ate the second piece. So, לרבא ליתא
מצוות. le-Rava leika mitzvot.
If it's a formal requirement of two, then you don't have two.
At the time you did your sin, your act, there was only
one. בעידנא דאכל ישראל, be-idna de-achal Yisrael,
when the Jew is eating, there was only one. לרבי זירא אי
אפשר לברר איסורא. le-Rabbi Zeira ee efshar levareir issura. According to Rabbi
Zeira, even when you did your act, there was no potential of
clarifying it, because the other piece was no longer around. Right? If
the non-Jew ate it after you, the other piece, it doesn't matter.
At the time of your act, in theory, it could have been
determined. We could have checked the other piece. But if at the
time of your act the other piece wasn't around anymore, you'd also
get off the hook. But לרב נחמן, le-Rav Nachman, איקבע איסורא. ikva
issura. According to Rav Nachman, at least we knew that there had
been an איסור issur present, even though at the time of your
act there was only one piece. Now that goes a little bit
against my explanation, because then we're saying that even if at the
time of your act there was only one piece, and now it's
just a question, what is this piece, איסור issur or היתר, heter,
right? That for him you would still bring an אשם asham if
we knew that at one time there was an איסור issur present.
So it's not exactly as far as I was pushing, איסור issur
is right now there's an איסור issur in front of you and
the question is did you choose it. Even if right now there's
only one piece, since there had been an איסור issur present, that
is enough to make it a concrete issue and to say you
bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Okay, so now we're going to
go through the same three proofs that you don't need שתי חתיכות
shtei chatichot with the same three answers, or the same one answer.
איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן. eitivei Rava le-Rav Nachman. So Rava asked on
Rav Nachman. רבי אליעזר אומר כוי חייבין על חלבו אשם תלוי. Rabbi
Eliezer omer koy chayavin al chelvo asham talui. You bring for the
fat of a כוי koy an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So the
גמרא, Gemara, so you see that you don't need two pieces. It's
איקבע איסורא. ikva issura. רבי אליעזר לא בעי שתי חתיכות. Rabbi Eliezer
lo baei shtei chatichot. Rabbi Eliezer doesn't require
that. איתיביה, eitivei, ספק בן תשעה לראשון או בן שבעה לאחרון. safek
ben tisha la-rishon o ben shiva la-acharon. You don't know whether it
was a child of the first or the second, so whether there
was a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum or not. וחייבין באשם תלוי.
ve-chayavin be-asham talui. And the fact that they've been having sex and
now it turns out that it might be עריות, arayot, they have
to bring an אשם תלוי, asham talui, even though it's not איקבע
איסורא, ikva issura, because you don't know that she was, that there
was ever an established איסור issur here. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הא מני רבי אליעזר היא. ha mani Rabbi Eliezer hi. That's Rabbi
Eliezer. Now I should say that you could have argued, once we
see that even when the piece is eaten, it's called איקבע איסורא
ikva issura because we know there was an איסור issur at one
time, you could have argued that this was איקבע איסורא. ikva issura.
Why? Because this woman at one time had a, was אסור assur
to her brother, when the other husband was still, when his brother
was still alive, her brother-in-law. Then she was an אשת איש, eishet
ish, she was אשת אח. eishet ach. Okay, so her איסור issur
status was already established and now the question is just did it
change or not. Okay, and so תוספות Tosafot discusses those issues. If
it's about איקבע איסורא, ikva issura, do you really need two pieces?
For example, you'll remember one of the cases in the משנה Mishna
was a case about ספק שבת ספק חול, safek Shabbos safek chol,
right? And you do a מלאכה. melacha. Where's איקבע איסורא? ikva issura?
For here שבת, Shabbos, here חול, chol, which one did I do,
right? So תוספות Tosafot says, no, the איקבע איסורא ikva issura would
be you did a מלאכה melacha on מוצאי שבת בין השמשות, Motzaei
Shabbos bein ha-shmashot, Saturday night בין השמשות. bein ha-shmashot. Why is it
איקבע איסורא? ikva issura? Because it had already been שבת Shabbos and
now you just don't know if שבת Shabbos is over. So the
fact that it had been שבת Shabbos and you just don't know
if it ended, that's enough for איקבע איסורא. ikva issura. So it's
very interesting. איקבע איסורא ikva issura might not now require, especially if
we say if one piece was removed, it might not require two
things in front of you. It's enough that the איסור issur has
been established. But if that's true, then you wonder why the גמרא
Gemara didn't give this answer in the case by the יבום yibum
case.
Yes. This seems to be more like the כוי koy because the
status of בין השמשות bein ha-shmashot isn't really...
Yes, but the difference is by, is indeterminable. But the difference is
there you started with it being שבת. Shabbos. And the question is
did שבת Shabbos end or not. By the כוי koy you never
started clearly with an איסור. issur. Okay, anyway, that's what תוספות Tosafot
says and in fact that's for you could have theoretically applied it
to יבום yibum as well. There's ways to distinguish. But I just,
okay, there's ways to distinguish. But my point being that once we
move to איקבע איסורא, ikva issura, it becomes a more conceptual issue.
Did you start with איסור, issur, not is, but based on what
the גמרא Gemara says if one was eaten, not is there איסור
issur in front of you. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues, third
example,
established, the איסור issur has already been established. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this,
where are we? איתיביה רבא, eitivei Rava, we just did that, נמצאת
שלא טמאה בתוך הקורבן. nimtzet she-lo tmeia be-toch ha-korban. If the blood
was on his thing he wiped with and clearly she was a
נדה niddah when they were having sex, so they bring a קורבן.
korban. נמצאת שלא שבעה ימים אחר כך, nimtzet she-lo shiva yamim achar
kach, and it's right after. In other words, טמאים וחייבים בקרבן, Tmeim
v'chayavim b'korban, you assume that she was a נדה Niddah and therefore
they're both טמא Tamei and they bring a קרבן. Korban. נמצא שלה
אחר זמן, Nimtza shelah achar zman, if it's on hers afterwards, so
you don't know whether she was a נדה Niddah at the time,
טמאים מספק ופטורים מן הקרבן, Tmeim misafek u'pturim min hakorban, you don't
bring a קרבן Korban because you don't know if she was a
נדה Niddah at the time. ותניא עלה, V'tanya alah, we have a
ברייתא, Braita, וחייבים באשם תלוי, V'chayavim b'asham talui, you bring an אשם
תלוי. Asham talui. So again you see that was not נקבע איסורא,
Nikva issura, that clearly not, it was the opposite. She started off
as being a non-נדה, Niddah, okay, and nevertheless you bring an אשם
תלוי. Asham talui. It's one חתיכה Chaticha as it was, it's not
נקבע איסורא. Nikva issura. So the obvious answer here is again רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. For some reason, אישתיק, Ishtik, he didn't respond. It's
not clear why he didn't respond, he could have easily said רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. לבתר דנפק, L'vatar d'nafak,
after he left in front of רבא, Rava, after רב נחמן Rav
Nachman left רבא, אמר Rava amar, מאי טעמא לא אמרי Amri, ליה,
why didn't I say to him דהא מני רבי מאיר היא, D'ha
mani Rabbi Meir hi, that it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir here? It's
funny because obviously he could have said רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's
what he's been saying, but now he realizes that I could have
even said that it's not only רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, there's a
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position out there that also says you don't
know נקבע איסורא. Nikva issura. What's the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position?
דלא בעי נקבע איסורא, D'lo ba'ei nikva issura,
he doesn't need נקבע איסורא. Nikva issura. דתניא, D'tanya, where do you
see this? השוחט אשם תלוי בחוץ. Hashocheit asham talui bachutz.
Now here we're going to get, I'm not going to get into
this in detail because we're going to see it later. It's the
whole question, right, if you find out later that you definitely didn't
sin, you don't bring an אשם תלוי. Asham talui. What happens, however,
if you sanctified your animal as an אשם תלוי Asham talui and
then you found out you didn't sin? Does it turn out that
you did not, does it turn out it was חולין? Chullin? What
happens if you sanctified it and brought it and it turns out
you didn't sin? Did you accidentally bring חולין בעזרה? Chullin b'azarah? Okay,
so that's an interesting question how those things change.
So if you didn't sin, right, he should have brought a חטאת?
Chatat? Well, yeah, okay, maybe.
But okay, maybe. Anyway, we'll talk about all that later. The question
is, you went ahead and you took an אשם תלוי Asham talui
and you slaughtered it outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Are you
חייב Chayav for שחוטי חוץ? Shechutei chutz? Now, so if it turns
out that you didn't sin about the reason you're bringing the אשם
תלוי, Asham talui, it could turn out that it was never really
a קרבן Korban and therefore you never really slaughtered a קרבן Korban
outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So are you חייב Chayav or
not? So, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: השוחט אשם תלוי
בחוץ, Hashocheit asham talui bachutz, רבי מאיר מחייב, Rabbi Meir mechayev, you're
חייב Chayav for שחוטי חוץ, Shechutei chutz, וחכמים פוטרים, V'chachamim potrim, and
the חכמים Chachamim exempt you. Now, how does this prove that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir does not need נקבע איסורא? Nikva issura? What does
this have to do with whether it has to do with the
status of an אשם תלוי Asham talui whatever, what does it have
to do with נקבע איסורא? Nikva issura? So רש"י Rashi says that
we're talking about a case that you made it an אשם תלוי
Asham talui for a sin that was not נקבע איסורא, Nikva issura,
for a sin that was, I don't know, like the כוי Koy
case, and you made an אשם תלוי. Asham talui. And therefore רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're חייב Chayav because it's definitely, it still
has a status of an אשם, Asham, וחכמים V'chachamim say you're not
חייב Chayav because they say, oh, it wasn't נקבע איסורא, Nikva issura,
so
you really weren't חייב Chayav in an אשם. Asham. Of course, that's
a little strange because then they're not really discussing the issue of
שחוטי חוץ Shechutei chutz or not, they're really just discussing when are
you חייב Chayav in an אשם, Asham, was it נקבע איסורא Nikva
issura or not. So רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom has a fascinating read.
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, remember, שחוטי חוץ Shechutei chutz is one
of the things you're חייב Chayav in a קרבן Korban for. What
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says is, what happens when you slaughter an
אשם תלוי בחוץ? Asham talui bachutz? You have a ספק שחוטי חוץ.
Safek shechutei chutz. If it turns out, right, if it turns out
that you hadn't done the sin, it wouldn't have been a קרבן.
Korban. If it turns out you had done it or whatever, it
would be a קרבן. Korban. So did you do שחוטי חוץ? Shechutei
chutz? It's a ספק. Safek. So when רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
you're חייב, Chayav, what do you bring according to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir when you're חייב Chayav when you slaughter the אשם תלוי בחוץ?
Asham talui bachutz? Not a חטאת, Chatat, an אשם תלוי! Asham talui!
Because you might have done a שחוטי חוץ. Shechutei chutz. וחכמים V'chachamim
say you're פטור. Patur. Why do they say you're פטור? Patur? Because
it's not נקבע איסורא. Nikva issura. Okay, because you don't know for
sure that you actually, now, now of course you could say again,
isn't it נקבע איסורא Nikva issura because you sanctified the animal? You
clearly have קדשים Kodashim in front of you. It's only the possibility
that it might change its status. So again, that goes to the
question that I've been saying, whether נקבע איסורא Nikva issura requires starting
with two pieces or is it enough that a status has already
been established? But bracketing that for the moment, רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom
is a beautiful read here that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is מחייב
Mechayev you an אשם תלוי Asham talui even though it's not נקבע
איסורא. Nikva issura. So you see, says, I could have just said
the same way I was saying רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, I could
have said it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that doesn't need נקבע איסורא.
Nikva issura. Let's just read one more sentence. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
אמאי, Amai, why, why was he saying, oh, I should have said
it was רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? לימא ליה דרבי אליעזר היא, Leima
lei d'Rabbi Eliezer hi, say it's רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's what
you've been saying until now anyway. הא קמשמע לן דרבי מאיר בשיטת
רבי אליעזר קאי, Ha kamashma lan d'Rabbi Meir b'shitat Rabbi Eliezer kai,
because I could have even, meaning yes, I could have said it's
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that's what I've been saying to him, but
I could have even backed it up further and said there's even
another תנא Tanna that holds you don't need נקבע איסורא, Nikva issura,
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But why he didn't, I don't know, it's
not clear. See, he was a little, he was a little
overwhelmed, he was keeping on, I
don't know. Anyway, but the
point It's not a חייב כרת. chayav kares. It won't lead to
a קרבן. korban. Ah, okay. Yes.
So, you know, suppose in עושה תמורה ותמורה oseh tmura u-tmura you
can have an אשם תלוי asham talui and an אשם ודאי. asham
vaday.
Right, so that's interesting, well but you don't bring the אשם תלוי
asham talui for the אשם ודאי. asham vaday. You bring the אשם
תלוי asham talui for the sin of שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. Okay.
And anyway, but רבינו גרשום's Rabbeinu Gershom read is clearly the best.
Okay. Anyway, so now we have three nice questions. A, you have
a position you don't need שתי חתיכות. shtei chatichot. We have a
position you do need שתי חתיכות shtei chatichot with three reasons: plus
גזירת הכתוב gziras ha-kasuv or אפשר לברר efshar l'varer or איקבע איסורא.
ikva issura. And now the גמרא gemara goes on with some scenarios.
Okay, let's take a look. אמר רבא בר אבויה אמר רב: Amar
Rava bar Avuya amar Rav: חתיכה ספק של חלב ספק של שומן.
chaticha safeik shel cheilev safeik shel shuman. So if you have a
חתיכה chaticha you don't know if it's חלב cheilev or שומן, shuman,
like we've been talking, one חתיכה, chaticha, ואכלה, v'achala, you ate it,
פלוגתא דרבי אליעזר וחכמים. plugta d'Rabbi Eliezer v'Chachamim. So we—this is the
debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים. Chachamim. We've been
saying that until now. What's the חידוש? chiddush? So תוספות Tosafot actually
says that, and you'll see the גמרא gemara it'll get even a
little bit more complicated in a minute, and it seems like we
have totally forgotten our previous discussion that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds
this position. So תוספות Tosafot says one of these is רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar and one of these is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay,
that it's a different—it's not the same. He says before it was
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, here it's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. It's not
the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer we were talking about before. Okay, so
now which רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer are we talking about? So a
new one. We're going to see in a minute. מאי איריא כי
אכלה? Mai irya ki achala? What do you mean if you ate
it? אפילו לא אכלה נמי. Afilu lo achala nami. Even if you
didn't eat, you could bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Why? Since
when? What did you do wrong? Why would you bring an אשם
תלוי? asham talui? Because we have a fascinating position of רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה, mishna, רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, again let's ignore
the previous רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, that would be רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, מתנדב אדם אשם תלוי בכל יום.
misnadeiv adam asham talui bechol yom. Every day you can bring an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. You see this idea about being a sort
of like, you know, the Jewish guilt or, you know, or OCD
and oh my god, maybe I did this wrong, maybe I did
that wrong. That has a good history. That has a good—a good
lineage. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said every day you might have sinned,
right? והוא רחום יכפר עון. V'hu rachum y'chapeir avon. Every day you
might have sinned. So therefore, if you want to bring an אשם
תלוי asham talui every day because you might—because today who knows, maybe
I did something wrong today. Now you're not חייב. chayav. You don't
have a concrete basis for knowing, but because of the theoretical possibility,
you're allowed to bring an אשם תלוי asham talui just because of
the generic possibility of doubt, you know, of the possibility of sin.
So therefore, the גמרא gemara says why did you say according to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer if you ate one חתיכה chaticha you bring
an אשם תלוי? asham talui? You know, even if you didn't do
anything concretely wrong, you could bring an אשם תלוי asham talui because
of the possibility. Now the obvious difference is is that in this
case it's מתנדב. misnadeiv. You can opt to bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. You're allowed to, not that you're obligated to. But תוספות
Tosafot is saying—explaining the גמרא gemara the following way: how do you
know רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says even one חתיכה? chaticha? Because you're
inferring it from רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer general approach that you can
bring an אשם תלוי asham talui even with abstract doubt. Abstract doubt
obviously is not שתי חתיכות. shtei chatichot. But if that's the רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you're basing it on, all you know—you don't even
have to eat. All you know is he says you can opt
to do it. And if we're talking about opting to do it,
then who needs to actually eat it? And if we're not talking
about opting, we're talking about required, well we don't know when רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say you're required or not. So make up
your mind. If it's required, we don't know his position. If it's
about opting, you don't even need to eat to go ahead and
bring it. So let's see what the גמרא gemara answers.
So the גמרא gemara says, אמר רב אשי רבי אליעזר אליבא דבבא
בן בוטא. Amar Rav Ashi Rabbi Eliezer aliba d'Bava ben Buta.
We're talking about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer according to בבא בן בוטא.
Bava ben Buta. What is this? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the
משנה, mishna, אלא אומרים לו, ela omrim lo, it should be אומרים
לי, omrim li, המתן עד שתכנס לבית הספק. hamtein ad shetikanes l'veis
hasafeik. The גמרא gemara was that בבא בן בוטא Bava ben Buta
said—followed רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer followed בבא
בן בוטא, Bava ben Buta, and he—בבא בן בוטא Bava ben Buta
said, I would have brought a קרבן אשם תלוי korban asham talui
even the day after יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But my—because even though
I just had everything atoned for me, I would have brought it.
Who knows? You know, it's like saying והוא רחום v'hu rachum as
soon as you finish יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. He says, but he
says, my friends said to me, you know, wait at least a
day till maybe you've actually sinned. Don't bring it the morning after
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, so what's the point here? The point
is that even within רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you need there to
be at least some smidgen of a doubt. So why did we
say when you ate the piece you're חייב? chayav? Because we don't
mean—we mean רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in this approach, which is even
when you can give an אשם תלוי asham talui by a נדבה,
nedava, there has to have been some basis on which you are
doing it. So again, what we have discussed here is is that
there's an opinion that you can opt to do an אשם תלוי
asham talui even for a very abstract doubt, which is clearly not
שתי חתיכות. shtei chatichot. The question that even here in the conclusion
the גמרא's gemara unclear about is, does that idea of being מתנדב
misnadeiv translate to being obligated when there's something very concretely wrong, even
one חתיכה? chaticha? Logically, those would go together. If אשם תלוי asham
talui does not
require—if to do it as an optional doesn't require שתי חתיכות, shtei
chatichot, then even to be obligated, it would seem that it only
requires some objective, you know, some grounds for saying that you've sinned.
It would not go all the way to the other extreme to
say that to be חייב chayav you need שתי חתיכות. shtei chatichot.
Anyway, so the גמרא gemara is now a little clear how it
exactly resolves this idea of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, but it seems to be that it's saying that there's also
a question in תוספות Tosafot how to read the conclusion, but it
seems to be that it's saying you know that at least if
you've done something concretely wrong at least apt to do it and
maybe even according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer even just one חתיכה
chaticha you're חייב chayav to do it. So you had a question
first?
Yeah, so in the so your point about saying וכל רחום vechol
rachum ten tzedaka achar יום כיפור Yom Kippur there is an opinion
at the end of יומא Yoma that we don't דאוון daven מעריב
Maariv when we דאוון daven נעילה. Ne'ilah. But we don't follow that.
Yeah, but that's actually that's actually about שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. It's
not about the מעריב. Maariv. סלח לנו? Selach lanu? Yeah, I know,
but that's not what
the debate is. That debate is about whether we just have רחמנא
תני Rachmana tany so we can get you can get to eating
faster. It's not because of those elements of it.
Okay, so you see so we still say that he have to
have eaten something so then according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer how
are we still doing it every day? I mean let's say you
know that's what I said. The גמרא's Gemara conclusion is unclear. Is
the גמרא Gemara saying that according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer even
to do it a נדבה nedava you need to actually eat something?
Well taking certainly that's not the power of רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer
statement. So again it's a little unclear what the question was, a
little unclear what the answer is, but it seems to be at
least the most comfortable position in the end to assume is to
say if you actually did something concretely problematic then you're חייב. chayav.
If you just have the possibility you know there's things to worry
about but not as really concretely problematic it's not the second after
יום כיפור Yom Kippur then you can do it in a נדבה.
nedava. Okay, that seems to be the answer but the answer is
not totally clear.
Yeah. Just some idea that your sins aren't counted between יום כיפור
Yom Kippur and the beginning of סוכות. Sukkot. Well not according to
this
גמרא. Gemara.
All right, no, all right, now okay so that whole issue within
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was a little unclear but again the point
though being is to acknowledge that there's an idea of a אשם
תלוי נדבה asham talui nedava which clearly does not require two חתיכות
chatichot and therefore maybe even the חיוב chiyuv of אשם תלוי asham
talui according to that opinion would not require two חתיכות. chatichot. Now
the גמרא Gemara goes on תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now we have
some scenarios. היו לפניו שתי חתיכות. Hayu lefanav shtei chatichot. You have
two pieces in front of you. אחת של שומן ואחת של חלב.
Achat shel shuman ve'achat shel chelev. This assumes obviously that you need
two חתיכות. chatichot. One of שומן shuman and one of חלב. chelev.
בא ישראל ואכל את הראשונה. Ba Yisrael ve'achal et harishonah. Now a
ישראל Yisrael ate the first one. So that's your classic case of
one חתיכה chaticha מבין שתי חתיכות mibein shtei chatichot אשם תלוי. asham
talui. בא עובד כוכבים ואכל את השנייה ba akum ve'achal et hashniyah
חייב. chayav. You're חייב chayav because at the time you did it
there were two pieces even though now you can no longer be
מברר mevarer even though now there are no longer two. At the
time you ate your one there was the other one and there
was אפשר לברר efshar levarer and there were two. וכן כלב וכן
עורב Vechein kelev vechein oreiv whoever eats the second one it's a
dog it's a raven doesn't matter. At the time you sinned and
you did your act there were two and you're חייב. chayav. Now
but let's say it's the reverse.
בא עובד כוכבים ואכל את הראשונה. Ba akum ve'achal et harishonah. There
were two. A non-Jew came and ate the first one. בא ישראל
ואכל את השנייה Ba Yisrael ve'achal et hashniyah and now ישראל Yisrael
came and he ate the second one. פטור. patur. You're exempt. Why?
Because at the time you did your act there were not two
there was only one. So if it's a formal requirement of two
there was only one when you did it. The non-Jew ate the
first one. If it's אפשר לברר efshar levarer it's not אפשר לברר
efshar levarer at the time you did it because the other one
wasn't around. The point is however this goes against the אקבע איסורא
ikvei issura because the גמרא Gemara had said that based on אקבע
איסורא ikvei issura you actually should be חייב chayav here. Okay and
for some reason the גמרא Gemara doesn't go back and challenge it
based on this ברייתא baraita again it would sort of assume like
it's been saying until now there are different tannaic opinions out there.
But anyway this says that does not follow that אקבע איסורא ikvei
issura idea and says you are פטור patur because at the time
you did it there was only one. Okay now רבי מחייב. Rabbi
mechayev. However in that case רבי Rabbi would say you are חייב.
chayav. Presumably not because he has a different reason for two but
presumably רבי Rabbi requires only one. So this idea do you require
two or one seems to be this debate. Let's keep on going.
אכל את הראשונה בשוגג והשנייה במזיד. Achal et harishonah beshogeg vehashniyah bemezid.
Let's say you ate the first one בשוגג beshogeg and then the
second one and then you realize oh my god one of these
might have been חלב. chelev. Well might as well eat the second
one. Okay so in that case חייב. chayav. For the first one
that was when you were בשוגג beshogeg so you're חייב אשם תלוי
chayav asham talui that's when there were two. For the second one
of course you're exempt number one you did it willfully so you're
exempt regardless and you're also exempt because there was only one by
the time you did the second one. Now הראשונה במזיד harishonah bemezid
let's say the first one you did willfully again not that you
definitely were sinning but you knew there might be a problem here
and you said what the heck and you ate one of them
anyway right so that we said before you won't bring an אשם
תלוי asham talui if you know it's a ספק safek at the
time of your doing the act. So when you did the first
one although there were two you were willful and therefore no
אשם תלוי. asham talui. והשנייה בשוגג vehashniyah beshogeg and the second one
was בשוגג beshogeg but the second one when you ate it there
was only one left. So therefore you can't bring for the first
it was במזיד mezid you can't bring for the second which was
בשוגג beshogeg because at the time you ate the second there was
only one left. So in that case פטור patur you're exempt. רבי
מחייב Rabbi mechayev again רבי Rabbi says you're חייב chayav because רבי
Rabbi says you only need one חתיכה. chaticha. Now אכל שתיהם במזיד
פטור achal shteihem bemezid patur if you ate both of them במזיד
mezid you're פטור patur that's obvious מכלום. miklum. שתיהם בשוגג shteihem beshogeg
if now if both of them were eaten בשוגג beshogeg שניהם חייב.
sheneihen chayav. Now what we have done actually here is introduced a
second person. Okay. So I ate the first one בשוגג beshogeg and
then Charlie ate the second one בשוגג. beshogeg. Now when I ate
the first one בשוגג beshogeg I have to bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. There were two pieces. When Charlie ate the second
one בשוגג, beshogeg,
what should Charlie's הלכה halacha be?
He should be פטור patur because there was only one piece at
that time. But this says both of them bring. Why do both
of them bring? Why does Charlie bring? So השני לא מן הדין,
hashani lo min hadin, so the second guy isn't bringing because he's
really technically
obligated, אלא שאם אתה אומר פטור, ela sheim ata omer patur, but
if you say Charlie is exempt, which we should expect to say
because there was only one piece left when he ate, כמאן דאמר
ראשון בחטאת, keman deamar rishon bechatat, you are implicitly saying how will
it be interpreted if we say Charlie is exempt? We'll say Charlie
didn't eat the חלב, chelev, so who ate the חלב? chelev? I
did. So then it will seem that I have to bring the
חטאת. chatat. Okay, so really I have to bring an אשם תלוי
asham talui because there was two and he doesn't because there was
one, but it will be interpreted as he didn't eat the wrong
thing, I did, and therefore I have to bring the חטאת. chatat.
Who wants to spend
all that money on that? Forget that, how about חולין בעזרה? chullin
ba'azarah? Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara is going to ask this. Now
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ומני, umani, who is this going
like? אי רבי, ei Rebbi, if it's רבי Rebbi that says you
don't need
שתי חתיכות, shtei chatichot, מן הדין ומני הוא, min hadin umani hu,
then Charlie should be bringing even though there was only one. רבי
Rebbi says who cares, two or one? So Charlie should be bringing.
אי רבנן, ei rabanan, if it's the rabbis that say you need
שתי חתיכות, shtei chatichot, משום דלא נתפס ראשון בחטאת, mishum delo nitpas
rishon bechatat, that we shouldn't make it implicit that the first one
is חייב בחטאת, chayav bechatat, נימא ליה לשני neima lei lashani we're
going to go say to Charlie אייתי חולין לעזרה, aiti chullin la'azarah,
bring חולין chullin to the עזרה? azarah? Charlie's exempt, how can he
bring an אשם? asham? אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, oh, we
have a way you can bring an אשם. asham. רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer here, because we talked about רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer before. There's
our friend רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer who lets us bring an אשם
asham even in, you know, for any reason. דאמר מתנדב אדם אשם
תלוי בכל יום, deamar mitnadev adam asham talui bechol yom, a person,
no, so then we will tell him to do it since he
has the possibility, we will tell him to do it so that
it doesn't make it look like I'm חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. Okay,
in order so that people don't start
wondering. הלכך אמרינן ליה, Hilkach amrinan lei, therefore we say to Charlie,
אייתי אשם תלוי, aiti asham talui, bring an אשם תלוי, asham talui,
ואתני, veatni, and stipulate.
אי אכל ראשון שומן הוא, Ei achal rishon shuman hu, listen, Charlie,
you'll say the following: if the first person ate שומן, shuman, then
that means I ate the חלב. chelev. So then I'm really, or
I might have eaten the חלב, chelev, I'm really חייב chayav in
this אשם תלוי asham talui because, not really because there was only
one חתיכה, chaticha, but okay, if there's a reason I would bring
a קרבן korban להוי כפרה. lehavei kaparah. So if I really ate
the wrong thing, this should be an atonement for my having eaten
the חלב. chelev. ואי לאו, Veilav, if I didn't eat the wrong
thing, if the rabbi ate the חלב chelev and I didn't, so
what? להוי נדבה, Lehavei nedavah, let it still be a generic אשם
תלוי. asham talui. Okay, so Charlie brings it because he's able to
bring it like רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. Now by the way, this
shows a hybrid of the position of שתי חתיכות shtei chatichot with
רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. Right? This is going according to the opinion
that you need שתי חתיכות shtei chatichot to be חייב, chayav, and
it says even when you're not חייב, chayav, like Charlie's not חייב,
chayav, he still has the רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer option of bringing
it even though it is just a generic possibility and one חתיכה
chaticha and so on. So that shows that even you can adopt
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that you have a free will, a נדבה
אשם תלוי nedavah asham talui for a generic possibility and still go
to the opposite extreme and say you need שתי חתיכות shtei chatichot
to be obligated. Is that clear? Right? You would have thought if
you can bring it as a generic possibility, you'd be obligated even
with one. But here we have a position, no, to be obligated
you need two, but if you're not obligated, you still have the
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer option. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
Yes, Charlie.
You could also do if I'm חייב chayav this is an אשם,
asham, if not this is a שלמים shelamim because the blood offering
is the
same on both. But then you have differences in terms of eating
them, right?
Only the כהנים Kohanim could eat it.
Yeah, that's possibly true, but we want it to look like you're
bringing an אשם, asham, so but I hear that, that's an interesting
thought.
Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. אכל ספק חלב ונודע לו, ספק חלב
ונודע לו. Achal safek chelev venoda lo, safek chelev venoda lo. Now
we're going to the other point of the משנה. Mishnah. How many
אשם תלוים asham taluim might you have to bring? So you ate
doubtful שומן, shuman, חלב, chelev, and then you realized, oh my god,
that might have been חלב. chelev. And then you forgot again and
then you ate some more of it. Okay, so and again and
again and again. How many אשמים ashamim do you bring? So in
the middle you realized you might have sinned. So רבי Rebbi says,
if you remember our, the משנה Mishnah said basically you bring as
many אשמים ashamim as you would have brought חטאות chataot had that
been a case of you had definitely sinned. אומר אני, Omer ani,
I say, says רבי, Rebbi, שכשם שמביא חטאת על כל אחת ואחת,
shekeshem shemeivi chatat al kol achat veachat, the same way had you
realized in the middle that you had definitely sinned and you would
bring multiple חטאות chataot when you remember in between, כך מביא אשם
תלוי על כל אחת ואחת, kach meivi asham talui al kol achat
veachat, you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui when you remember in
the middle that you might
have. רבי יוסי ורבי יהודה ורבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון Rebbi Yossi veRebbi
Yehuda veRebbi Eliezer veRebbi Shimon mean these three חכמים chachamim say אין
מביא אלא אשם תלוי אחד. ein meivi ela asham talui echad. No,
even if you've done that and you remember, remember, remember, there's only
one אשם תלוי. asham talui. Why? Why don't we say the ידיעה
yedi'ah makes you חייב chayav in multiple? שנאמר על שגגתו אשר שגג,
Shene'emar al shigagato asher shagag, for the error that he erred, which
is a very redundant
language, אפילו שגגות הרבה, afilu shigagot harbeh, even
for many שגגות, shigagot, if it's all for the same thing multiple
times as opposed to different sins, אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayav
ela achat. You only bring one. Now I want to take out
a second to say why is it... Our משנה Mishna was רבי.
Rabbi. Okay, but this is an opinion that even if you did
חלב chelev and דם dam and נותר, nosar, yes, you'd bring three,
but חלב חלב חלב, chelev chelev chelev, you only bring one even
if you remembered between. Why is it different than a חטאת? chatas?
So I think this says something interesting about the nature of אשם
asham in general, right, there's a question why is there a קרבן
korban called an אשם asham if it's about a sin? And one
explanation, it's a question if it really works consistently, but I've been
telling you from the very beginning that חטאת chatas is not all
about personal guilt. חטאת chatas is about the objective reality of a
sin, the proof being that תינוק שנשבה Tinok Shenishba and does, you
know, doesn't even know about שבת Shabbos and מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos
still brings a חטאת. chatas. There's the objective reality of sin that
has to be cleansed even and חטאת chatas can also be interpreted
as cleansing, not atonement, and that's what a חטאת chatas is. אשם
asham focuses on you the person. Think about the פסוק pasuk by
אשם. asham. אשם הוא אשום אשם להשם. Asham hu ashom asham la-Hashem.
You have, you know, been guilty to God. אשם asham is all
about about being, you know, ואשמה, ve-ashma, you know, it's about being
guilty, being at fault. So therefore, that seems harsh, but here's the
interesting thing about the אשם תלוי. asham talui. We don't know there's
an objective reality of sin. We don't know something has to be
cleansed. But what we do know is that you might require atonement
because you did something, you should have been, anyway, you should have
been more careful. Don't even get yourself into a position of ספק
safek sin. And B, you need something as the גמרא Gemara says
to protect you until we can cleanse the sin, until we actually
can bring the חטאת. chatas. So an אשם asham is much more,
certainly an אשם תלוי, asham talui, about you than about the sin.
Okay, and therefore, that's what I think this position is. Even if
you did חלב חלב חלב חלב, chelev chelev chelev chelev, it's if
it was about sin, there were possibly three sins out there that
each one needs to be cleansed separately. But if it's about you,
then it's basically you're all, you're complete, you know, you're at fault
for this whole category of things. It doesn't, it's not divided so
much by the different, by the different sins, especially if it's all
the same type of a sin.
So, you say if I ate חלב chelev and דם dam and
נותר, nosar, yes, so yes, yes, they're still different categories. If I'm
a generally a negligent person, right, and one day I'm negligent with
the car and the next day I'm negligent, you know, and I
go get into an accident and the next day I let, you
know, let something happen to the house, those are still, you know,
fundamentally different things that I am to blame for. Okay, but if
I was just completely irresponsible with the car this when I went
out and I got into three different accidents, it tends to focus
on one stupid thing that I was doing, right? So, so that
seems to be the difference. Anyway, so that's what I think this
is about. It's a fascinating position which is, which really hones in
actually the idea that this is more about the personal guilt than
about the sin and therefore multiple things of the same type is
only one. However, although there's a little letter by that opinion, it's
not the position of the משנה Mishna and here for once the
letter's in the wrong place, the רמב"ם Rambam rules like the משנה
Mishna and like רבי. Rabbi. That an אשם asham is just like
a חטאת chatas and when you remember in between, you bring multiple
אשמות.
ashamot. כחטאת כאשם Ke-chatas ke-asham here, right?
I know. Yes. So anyway, but it is interesting that there's this
other opinion there that focuses more on the person than on the
sin, but in the end we פוסקים pasken an אשם asham is
like a חטאת. chatas. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, כאן שנה רבי. kan shana Rabbi.
Now, now we're going to focus on what did רבי Rabbi mean
when he said it's like a חטאת? chatas? So we think what
רבי Rabbi means is the same way when a חטאת chatas when
you become aware in between each act that you definitely sinned, you
bring multiple חטאות. chataot. Here when you become aware in between each
one that you might have sinned, you bring
multiple אשמות. ashamot. But that's not how they're going to read it.
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira reads it, כאן שנה רבי ידיעות ספק מחלקות
לחטאות. kan shana Rabbi yedi'ot safek mechalkot le-chataot. That not that we
learn אשם asham from חטאת, chatas, we learn חטאת chatas from אשם.
asham. By אשם asham what type of awareness divides the acts? Being
aware that you might have sinned. So he says רבי Rabbi would
say that if you became aware that you might have sinned and
then at the end you found out you definitely sinned, you bring
multiple חטאות. chataot. You understand the scenario? I went ahead and I
ate this piece of thing. And I said, oh my God, that
might have been חלב. chelev. Then I ate it again. Oh my
God, it might have been חלב. chelev. Then I ate again. Okay,
and then at the end, I find out that it definitely was
חלב. chelev. So would I bring one חטאת chatas or three? So
he says, what interrupted those acts? A ספק ידיעה, safek yedi'ah, or
really ידיעת ספק, yedi'at safek, okay, knowledge of a doubt. Is that
enough once we're talking about חטאת, chatas, not אשם, asham, to break
it up? And he says yes. The same way by אשם asham
knowing I might breaks up the act, even for חטאת, chatas, not
just knowing I definitely, but even knowing I might have sinned breaks
up the act. That's how he's reading רבי. Rabbi. Not we learn
אשם asham from חטאת, chatas, we learn חטאת chatas from
אשם. asham. ידיעת ספק, yedi'at safek, knowing that I might have sinned,
מחלקות לחטאות mechalkot le-chataot is enough to divide. רבא Rava, אמר, no,
אין ידיעת ספק מחלקת לחטאות. ein yedi'at safek mechalket le-chataot. You read
it wrong. It's not whatever, not wrong, but whatever, I don't agree
with that reading. That does not divide. Only definite knowledge divides for
חטאת. chatas. אלא הכי קתני, Ela hachi katani, here's how to read
it.
כשם שאם הייתה לו ידיעה ודאי, Ke-shem she-im hayeta lo yedi'ah vadai,
it's an analogy, it's not the same type of knowledge. The same
way if you had a definite knowledge to interrupt, מביא חטאת על
כל אחת ואחת, mevi chatas al kol achat ve-achat, you'd bring a
separate
חטאת, chatas, כך, kach, so too by analogy,
אם הייתה לו... im hayeta lo...
So you need to know for sure it was
חטאת Chatas in order to bring multiple חטאות. Chata'os. אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lei Abaye, so Abaye said, והא לא תסבר דידיעה ספק מחלקת
לחטאות? Veha lo tisbar diyedi'a safeik mechallekes lachata'os? Do you really not
hold that a doubtful knowledge or a knowledge of a doubt is
enough to divide for חטאות? Chata'os? ואי סלקא דעתך ידיעה ספק אינה
מחלקת לחטאות, Ve'i salka dachach yedi'a safeik eina mechallekes lachata'os, if you
say it doesn't, וחטאת אחת מביא, vechatas achas meivi, and if you
have only no in-between that only you might have sinned and then
you did it multiple times, you would and then you found out
you definitely, you would only bring one חטאת. Chatas. אמאי מביא אשם
תלוי על כל אחת ואחת? Amai meivi asham talui al kol achas
ve'achas? Then why do you bring multiple אשם תלוים? Asham Taluis? Because
he's assuming that the comparison of אשם Asham to חטאת Chatas cannot
be by analogy, it has to be a direct application, right? You
understand the point? So do you make an analogy? Definite knowledge divides
חטאות, Chata'os, by analogy ספק safeik knowledge divides
אשמות. Ashamos. Abaye says no, no analogies. You have to directly apply
the rule. So if the rule by חטאת Chatas is only a
definite knowledge divides, then that can't be applied to an אשם Asham
because an אשם Asham you never have definite knowledge. So he assumes
it's not an analogy, it's a rule, and therefore to apply חטאת
Chatas to אשם, Asham, חטאת Chatas also has to be doubtful knowledge.
והתניא ותנן בברייתא, Vehatanya vesanan beraisa, the general rule is, כל שחלוקין
בחטאת, kol shechallukin bechatas, anything that's a basis for dividing for sin
offerings, חלוקין באשמות, challukin be'ashamos, divide for an אשם. Asham. So therefore
by an אשם Asham the only thing that divides is doubtful, that
must also divide by חטאת. Chatas. אמר ליה רבא בר חנן לאביי,
Amar lei Rava bar Chanan le'Abaye, Rava bar Chanan said back to
Abaye, so obviously the answer is obvious, no it doesn't have to
be the exact thing, it's an analogy. And now the other position
is going to get challenged. ולדידך כמאן דאמרת ידיעה ספק מחלקת לחטאות,
Uledidach keman de'amart yedi'a safeik mechallekes lachata'os, according to you that you
say doubtful knowledge divides for חטאות, Chata'os, אלא מעתה, ella me'ata, אכל
חלב לפני יום הכיפורים achal cheilev lifnei Yom HaKippurim and כזית חלב
אחר יום הכיפורים. vechazayis cheilev achar Yom HaKippurim. Now you have to
understand a couple of principles here. Number one,
when יום כיפור Yom Kippur passes, if a person definitely did a
sin and is חייב chayav a קרבן, korban, then just because יום
כיפור Yom Kippur passes he still has to bring the קרבן, korban,
he still has to bring the חטאת. Chatas. I mean some of
this is debated but this is anyway what we're assuming. If however
a person did a doubtful sin, we have a principle that יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, after יום כיפור Yom Kippur passes, you no longer
have to bring your אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. יום כיפור Yom Kippur
atones for the doubtful sin even though it does not atone, even
though you still have to bring the קרבן, korban, okay? So we're
assuming that יום כיפור Yom Kippur works like an אשם תלוי. Asham
Talui. That's principle number one. Principle number two is, and this is
very important, when we say that when you become aware it divides
for a חטאת, Chatas, there are two ways of explaining that. One
is psychological and the other is objective based on obligation. We normally
assume psychological. Oh, I became aware, then I forgot again, that divides
the acts. Since I became aware and then I forgot again, it
defines them as second, it's all psychological. But you'll remember for example
the other day we said like when six days of the week
passes, you know, it's as if you became aware. ימים שבינתיים הוו
ידיעה. Yamim shebeintayim havu yedi'a. Now if it's psychological that doesn't really
explain it. So there's another possibility which is not psychological, which is,
when I become aware that I sinned, I become obligated in a
חטאת, Chatas, right? At that moment. So once I became obligated in
a חטאת, Chatas, my obligation was for the past sin and now
something else is a new story. So it's not my becoming aware
that divides the acts, it's my obligation that therefore said that was
one חטאת Chatas for the previous, then I've done another thing, fine,
if I remember there it's another חטאת, Chatas, not the awareness. Now
why is this relevant? Because we're going to treat יום כיפור Yom
Kippur like a ספק ידיעה, safeik yedi'a, like you became aware in
doubt. Now if it was all about psychological, that would not make
any sense to divide the acts. But if it's because of obligation
it makes sense. Once יום כיפור Yom Kippur wipes away the past,
it's like then therefore the past חיוב chiyuv of אשם Asham cannot
connect to what comes after. Okay, so it's more the objective idea
of an אשם Asham and being obligated in אשם Asham or bringing
an אשם Asham that divides them, not psychological awareness. Now let's see
with that as a background what the question was. Let's take a
look. אמר ליה רבא בר חנן לאביי, Amar lei Rava bar Chanan
le'Abaye, so he
said to Abaye, לדידך דאמרת ידיעה ספק מחלקת לחטאות, ledidach de'amart yedi'a
safeik mechallekes lachata'os, אלא מעתה, ella me'ata, אכל כזית חלב לפני יום
הכיפורים, achal kezayis cheilev lifnei Yom HaKippurim, he ate a כזית kezayis
of חלב cheilev before יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, וכזית חלב אחר יום
הכיפורים, vechazayis cheilev achar Yom HaKippurim, and a כזית kezayis after, and
it was definitely חלב, cheilev, so it would have been two
חטאות. chata'os. ויום הכיפורים במקום אשם תלוי קאי, VeYom HaKippurim bimkom asham
talui ka'ei, יום כיפור Yom Kippur is in the middle, it works
like an אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, it wipes out your אשם תלוי
Asham Talui obligations. Now here you're not אשם תלוי, asham talui, here
you're a חטאת chatas person. But if you say ספק ידיעה safeik
yedi'a divides, so יום כיפור Yom Kippur should also divide. הכא נמי
דמייתי שתי חטאות? Hacha nami demayisi shtei chata'os? Would you say he
brings two sin offerings in this case because יום כיפור Yom Kippur
passed? והא בהעלם אחת אכלינהו, Veha behe'elem achas achlineihu, he ate it
all in one state of forgetfulness. Now the answer of course could
be אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, you do bring two חטאות,
chata'os, but okay. But anyway but again the point being that psychologically
you're not aware, העלם אחת, he'elem achas, but he's saying if you
say that ספק ידיעה, safeik yedi'a, that's not necessarily psychological, it means...
something that functions as a חיוב אשם תלוי. Chiyuv asham talui. So
the reality of יום כיפור Yom Kippur which functions as if it
was an אשם תלוי Asham talui should also divide. Are you going
to really say that that יום כיפור Yom Kippur divides two חטאות
Chataos obligations? So אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye ומאן לימא לן
דיום הכיפורים מכפר על דלא מיתידע ליה? Uman leima lan deYom HaKippurim
mechaper al d'lo mityada lei? דהא ודאי דמיתידע ליה. Deha vadai demityada
lei.
Who says יום כיפור Yom Kippur gets you out of your אשם
תלוי Asham talui obligation if you're not yet aware that you're obligated?
Maybe when we say יום כיפור Yom Kippur gets you out of
your אשם תלוי, Asham talui, it's only when you're aware that you
have sinned. And therefore since the whole construct of this question is
a person that is not aware that they might have sinned, right,
you might have sinned, so since the whole construct of this question
is a person that's not aware, בהעלמה אחת Be-helama achas from before
יום כיפור Yom Kippur to after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, he says
I'll argue that יום כיפור Yom Kippur won't be מכפר Mechaper for
him, it won't work like an אשם תלוי Asham talui for him.
אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said back, what
do you mean? הודע ולא הודע תנן. Hoda velo hoda tnan. The
משנה Mishna in יומא Yoma that talks about what יום כיפור Yom
Kippur atones for, it says whether it's known to you or not
known to you. So don't try to tell me that it doesn't
work if it's not known to you. So we're back to our
question. If יום כיפור Yom Kippur functions like an אשם תלוי Asham
talui and then that should divide two חטאות Chataos if a ספק
ידיעה Safek yedia divides two חטאות. Chataos. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar
lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye kept up his resistance and he said,
I'm sorry, איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say אמר ליה רבא בר
חנא לאביי Amar lei Rava bar Chana l'Abaye מה אילו אכל כזית
חלב שחרית ביום הכיפורים וכזית חלב במנחה ביום הכיפורים הכי נמי דמיחייב
שתי
חטאות? Ma ilu achal kezayis cheilev shacharis b'Yom HaKippurim v'kezayis cheilev b'mincha
b'Yom HaKippurim hachi nami demichayev shtei chataos? So it was a different
question, not before and after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but the morning
and the afternoon of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But the assumption is
that every minute of יום כיפור Yom Kippur is מכפר. Mechaper. So
he said, would you really say if you took a little break
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it wasn't enough you were eating, you
were eating חלב, Cheilev, and you took a little break between the
first כזית Kezayis and the second, that it would be two חטאות
Chataos even if it was בהעלמה אחת Be-helama achas just because there
was a few minutes of יום כיפור Yom Kippur in between that
should function like an אשם תלוי Asham talui and divide it? So
ספק ידיעה Safek yedia divides, that should divide, would you really say
that? So אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said back,
ומאן לימא לן דכל שעתא ושעתא מכפר? Uman leima lan dechol sha'ata
v'sha'ata mechaper? Who says every minute of יום כיפור Yom Kippur is
what atones? דילמא כולי יומא מעורתא. Dilma kulei yoma me-urta.
Maybe it's the whole day that atones only from like morning to,
you know, from the previous night to the following night. So just
that minute won't act like an אשם תלוי Asham talui and won't
break up then into two separate acts. So אמר ליה, Amar lei,
the question exactly what the גרסא Girsa is, רבא בר חנא טרדא,
Rava bar Chana tarda, which רש"י Rashi says טרדא Tarda is like
שוטה, Shoteh, okay, which is a lazy person or stupid person. What
do you mean? Of course every minute of יום כיפור Yom Kippur
is מכפר. Mechaper. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, הרי
שבא לידו ספק עבירה ביום הכיפורים, Harei sheba l'yado safek aveira b'Yom
HaKippurim,
if you had on יום כיפור Yom Kippur itself you did something
that might have sinned, it might be required and therefore it's might,
and because it's might, it's an אשם תלוי, Asham talui, אפילו עם
חשיכה, Afilu im chasheicha,
even if it was a minute before it got dark at the
end of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, פטור, Patur, שכל היום מכפר. Shechol
hayom mechaper. Every minute of the day atones. Every minute functions as
an אשם תלוי. Asham talui.
We had that before, like,
yes, I don't want to discuss that. Every minute functions as an
אשם תלוי. Asham talui. So now what we're saying to אביי Abaye
is, if you think a ספק ידיעה Safek yedia divides for חטאות,
Chataos, not for אשם, Asham, of course it works for אשם, Asham,
for חטאות, Chataos, then again assuming it's not the psychological reality of
ספק ידיעה, Safek yedia, assuming it's ספק ידיעה Safek yedia the way
it functions to create a חיוב Chiyuv of an אשם תלוי, Asham
talui, then יום כיפור Yom Kippur which is like an אשם תלוי
Asham talui should also divide and that seems absurd that it would
that bring two חטאות Chataos because יום כיפור Yom Kippur intervened. So
we don't have an answer to that. Let's read a little bit
more. מתיב רב אידי בר אבין. Masiv Rav Idi bar Avin. אכל
ושתה בהעלמה אחת. Achal v'shasa be-helama achas. On יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
right,
by the way, if you eat on יום כיפור Yom Kippur בשוגג,
B'shogeg, you bring a חטאת Chatas because that's חייב כרת. Chayav kares.
Let's say you ate and drank all in one state of having
forgotten it's יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So therefore אינו חייב אלא אחת,
Eino chayav ela achas, אלא חטאת אחת. Ela chatas achas. You bring
one חטאת Chatas because eating and drinking is all the same prohibition
of not fasting. והא בין אכילה לשתייה אי אפשר דלא הויא שעה
ביום דמיתידע ליה Veha bein achila l'shtiya ee efshar d'lo havya sha'a
bayom demityada lei ומכפר ליה Umechaper lei דיום הכיפורים במקום אשם תלוי
קאי. DeYom HaKippurim bimkom asham talui kai. Same question as before. Presumably
you ate, you took a little break, and you drank. Now how
do we know that happened? Okay, but let's assume that that's the
case. It says, so we don't, if we're not going to absurdly
limit it. So do you mean to tell me the guy ate
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, waited a minute, took a drink, right?
So we say one חטאת, Chatas, but again according to you that
minute of יום כיפור Yom Kippur functions like an אשם תלוי Asham
talui and should divide it up into two separate חטאות. Chataos. So
it's the same question but here asked very concretely from a משנה
Mishna that seems to prove one חטאת Chatas even if presumably there
was a few minutes between the eating and the drinking. Okay, there
should have been minute enough minutes for you to be aware. Now
it's interesting, here the phrase of דהויא שעה ביום דמיתידע ליה. Dehavya
sha'a bayom demityada lei. This gets back to the psychological aspect. Since
there were a few minutes in between that theoretically you could have
become aware, and since יום כיפור Yom Kippur functions like an אשם
תלוי, Asham talui, it should be as if you became aware. So
this is always the question, when we say ידיעה Yedia divides, is
it because of the psychological, and here the point is because in
theory you could have been aware, or is it about the reality
that the אשם תלוי Asham talui or the חיוב Chiyuv divides? Anyway,
either way, it is saying why there is it only one חטאת,
Chatas, it should be two, if ספק ידיעה Safek yedia divides יום
כיפור Yom Kippur should divide. So ואי סלקא דעתך, V'ei salka dach'tach,
I just read that,
ידיעה Yediya ספק מחלקת לחטאות divides, this should also lead to two
חטאות. Chatatot. אמרי, Amri, so you could say, תאמר רבי זירא לרבי,
Teimar Rabbi Zeira l'Rabbi, finally we say, all right, you're right. When
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said that a doubtful ידיעה divides, that was
explaining רבי, Rabbi, right? רבי Rabbi said you bring multiple אשם תלויs.
Asham Taluy So according to רבי Rabbi you bring multiple אשם תלויs,
Asham Taluy the same way a ספק ידיעה Saffek Yediya divides for
אשם, Asham, a ספק ידיעה Saffek Yediya divides for חטאת. Chatat. הא
רבנן היא. Ha Rabbanan hee. If you have any evidence against me,
that's the rabbis who argue on רבי Rabbi that say you don't
bring multiple אשמות. Ashamot. So they don't have to get into this
whole mess. But רבי Rabbi that says you bring multiple אשמות, Ashamot,
the same way a ספק ידיעה Saffek Yediya divides for אשם, Asham,
it divides from חטאת. Chatat. Let's just finish this up. דהא מדסיפא
רבי היא. D'ha mid'seifa Rabbi hee. One minute, the end of that
whole משנה Mishna about eating is רבי, Rabbi, דקתני, d'katani, ששתה ציר
ומורייס. sheshata tzir u'moryas. The end of that משנה Mishna about eating
and drinking says, if somebody drank fish brine or some other type
of thing like that, פטור. Patur. Then you're exempt because that's not
real food on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it doesn't really sate you.
החומץ, Ha'chometz, implicitly with something not as bad as that, but vinegar,
חייב. Chayav. ומני רבי? U'mani Rabbi? That and that implication that you're
חייב Chayav for vinegar on יום כיפור Yom Kippur is רבי. Rabbi.
How do we know that? דתניא, D'tanya, we taught a ברייתא, Braita,
חומץ אין משיבת הנפש. Chometz ein meshivat hanefesh.
Vinegar does not sate the sate your soul, would not negate your
fast. רבי אומר אומר אני חומץ משיבת הנפש. Rabbi omer omer ani
chometz meshivat hanefesh. It does sate the soul. So this משנה Mishna
that spoke about eating and drinking, the end of it by only
excluding fish brine and implicitly vinegar is a problem, shows that we're
dealing with רבי. Rabbi. And since we're dealing with רבי, Rabbi, you
can't get out of the beginning of the משנה Mishna and say
it's not רבי. Rabbi.
Of course we
can.
ומידסיפא רבי, U'mid'seifa Rabbi, since the end is
רבי, Rabbi, רישא נמי רבי. Reisha nami Rabbi. אמרי, so you could
say, no, like Mike, סיפא רבי רישא רבנן. Seifa Rabbi reisha Rabbanan.
Okay, the end is רבי, Rabbi, the beginning is the רבנן. Rabbanan.
So we will pick up with this issue tomorrow about whether ספק
ידיעה Saffek Yediya divides or does not divide after your סדר. Seder.
Everybody should have a חג כשר ושמח, Chag Kasher V'sameach, a good
סדר, Seder, and make sure to do your ביטול חמץ Bittul Chametz
sometime before the end of before the.